You know, we wake up in the morning,
تعلمون، نحن نستيقظ صباحاً
you get dressed, put on your shoes,
ترتدون الملابس، و تضعون أحذيتكم،
you head out into the world.
و تخرجون لتواجهون العالم.
You plan on coming back, getting undressed,
و تخططون للعودة، و تخلعون ملابسكم،
going to bed,
و تذهبون إلى النوم،
waking up, doing it again,
تستيقظون، وتقومون بكلّ ذلك مجدّدا،
and that anticipation, that rhythm,
وهذا التّوقع، ذلك الإيقاع،
helps give us a structure
يساعد على إعطاءنا بنية
to how we organize ourselves and our lives,
حول كيف ننظم أنفسنا وحياتنا،
and gives it a measure of predictability.
ويعطيها مقياس للتنبؤ.
Living in New York City, as I do,
العيش في مدينة نيويورك، مثلما أعيش أنا،
it's almost as if, with so many people doing so many things
تقريباً كما لو، مع الكثير من الناس يقومون بأشياء كثيرة
at the same time in such close quarters,
في الوقت نفسه في مثل هذه المساكن الضيقة،
it's almost like life is dealing you extra hands
تقريباً مثل أن الحياة تعرض عليك أيادي إضافية
out of that deck.
من على ذلك المركب.
You're never, there's just, juxtapositions are possible
لا يمكنك ابدأ، هناك فقط، تجاورات ممكنة
that just aren't, you don't think they're going to happen.
ذلك لا يكون، لا تعتقد انها سوف تحدث.
And you never think you're going to be the guy
ولا تعتقد ابدأ انك سوف تكون الرجل
who's walking down the street
الذي يمشي الشارع
and, because you choose to go down one side or the other,
ولانك تختار للنزول إلى جانب واحد أو آخر،
the rest of your life is changed forever.
ستتغير بقية حياتك إلى الأبد.
And one night, I'm riding the uptown local train.
وفي ليلة ما، يقلني قطار المدينة.
I get on. I tend to be a little bit vigilant
أركب. أميل أن أكون يقظا قليلاً
when I get on the subway.
عندما أستقل مترو الأنفاق.
I'm not one of the people zoning out with headphones
أنا لست واحداً من الناس الذين يشردون واضعين سماعات الرأس
or a book.
أو مع كتاب.
And I get on the car, and I look, and I
وأركب السيارة، وأنظر، وأنا
notice this couple,
ألاحظ هذا الزوج،
college-aged, student-looking kids,
من في سن الجامعة، و أطفال يبدون كطلبة،
a guy and a girl, and they're sitting next to each other,
رجل وفتاة، جالسان بجوار بعضهما البعض،
and she's got her leg draped over his knee,
واضعة ساقها على ركبته،
and they're doing -- they have this little contraption,
وهم على وضعهم--لديهم هذا الجهاز الصغير،
and they're tying these knots,
وهم يربطون تلك العقد
and they're doing it with one hand,
وهم يفعلون ذلك مع يد واحدة،
they're doing it left-handed and right-handed very quickly,
أنهم يفعلون ذلك باليد اليسرى واليد اليمنى بشكل سريع جداً،
and then she'll hand the thing to him and he'll do it.
ثم قالت أنها سوف تسلم الشيء له وأنه سوف يفعل ذلك.
I've never seen anything like this.
لم أر أي شيء من هذا القبيل.
It's almost like they're practicing magic tricks.
أنها تقريبا مثل ما كنت تمارس الخدع السحرية.
And at the next stop, a guy gets on the car,
وفي المحطة التالية، رجل يدخل العربة،
and he has this sort of visiting professor look to him.
ولديه هذا النوع من نظرة أستاذ زائر له.
He's got the overstuffed leather satchel
لديه الحقيبة الجلدية المتخمة
and the rectangular file case and a laptop bag
والملف المستطيل وحقيبة الكمبيوتر المحمول
and the tweed jacket with the leather patches,
وسترة التويد مع بقع جلدية،
and — (Laughter) —
و--(ضحك)-
he looks at them, and then
ينظر لهم، ومن ثم
in a blink of an eye, he kneels down in front of them,
في غمضة عين، يركع إلى أسفل أمامهم،
and he starts to say,
و يبدأ بقول،
"You know, listen, here's how you can do it. Look,
"تعلمون، انظروا، هنا كيف يمكنك أن تفعلوا ذلك. انظروا،
if you do this -- " and he takes the laces out of their hand,
إذا كنت تفعل هذا--"و يأخذ الأربطة من أيديهم،
and instantly, he starts tying these knots,
وعلى الفور، يبدأ بربط هذه العقد،
and even better than they were doing it, remarkably.
وحتى أفضل مما كانوا يفعلون ذلك، على نحو رائع.
And it turns out they are medical students
واتضح أنهم طلاب الطب
on their way to a lecture about the latest
في طريقهم إلى محاضرة حول أحدث
suturing techniques, and he's the guy giving the lecture.
تقنيات الغرز، وهو الرجل الذين يعطي المحاضرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So he starts to tell them, and he's like,
فبدأ يقول لهم، ومثل،
"No, this is very important here. You know,
"لا، هذا مهم جداً هنا. أنت تعرف
when you're needing these knots,
عندما كنت تحتاج إلى هذه العقد،
it's going to be, you know, everything's
ستكون، تعلمون، لكل شيء
going to be happening at the same time, it's going to be --
على وشك أن يحدث في نفس الوقت، سيكون -
you're going to have all this information coming at you,
ستكون لديك كل هذه المعلومات آتية إليك،
there's going to be organs getting in the way,
ستكون هناك أعضاء في الطريق،
it's going to be slippery,
ستكون زلقة،
and
و
it's just very important that you be able to do these
أنه فقط مهم جداً أن تكونوا قادرين على القيام بهذه
beyond second nature, each hand, left hand, right hand,
أبعد من العادات، كل يد، اليد اليسرى، اليد اليمنى،
you have to be able to do them without seeing your fingers."
عليك أن تكون قادراً على القيام بها دون رؤية أصابعك. "
And at that moment, when I heard that,
وفي تلك اللحظة، عندما استمعت إلى ذلك،
I just got catapulted out of the subway car into a night
قفزت بذهني من عربة مترو الإنفاق في ليلة
when I had been getting a ride in an ambulance
عندما كنت في سيارة إسعاف
from the sidewalk where I had been stabbed
من على الرصيف حيث طعنت
to the trauma room of St. Vincent's Hospital in Manhattan,
إلى غرفة الصدمات بمستشفى "سانت فنسنت" في "مانهاتن"،
and what had happened was
وما حدث كان أن
a gang had come in from Brooklyn.
عصابة أتت من "بروكلين".
As part of an initiation for three of their members,
كجزء من التكريس لثلاثة من أعضائها،
they had to kill somebody,
كان عليهم قتل شخص ما،
and I happened to be the guy walking down Bleecker Street
وصادف أن أكون الرجل الذي يسير في شارع "بليكر"
that night,
في تلك الليلة،
and they jumped on me without a word.
وقفزوا علي من دون كلمة.
One of the very lucky things,
واحدة من الأشياء المحظوظة جداً
when I was at Notre Dame, I was on the boxing team,
عندما كنت في "نوتردام"، كنت في فريق الملاكمة،
so I put my hands up right away, instinctively.
لذا فوراً وضعت يدي فوق ، بصورة غريزية.
The guy on the right had a knife with a 10-inch blade,
الرجل على اليمين كان لدية سكين بشفرة 10 بوصة،
and he went in under my elbow,
وجهها تحت كوعي،
and it went up and cut my inferior vena cava.
وارتفعت وقطعت وريدي الأجوف السفلي.
If you know anything about anatomy,
إذا كنت تعرف أي شيء عن علم التشريح،
that's not a good thing to get cut,
هذا الشيء سيء أن يقطع
and everything, of course, on the way up,
وكل شيء، بالطبع، فوقه،
and then — I still had my hands up —
ومن ثم، كان يدي لا يزالان فوق —
he pulled it out and went for my neck,
أخرج السكينة وذهب لرقبتي،
and sunk it in up to the hilt in my neck,
وغرزها إلى مقبضها في عنقي،
and I got one straight right punch
ولكمت لكمة مباشرة
and knocked the middle guy out.
أطاحت بالرجل الذي بالمنتصف.
The other guy was still working on me,
الرجل الآخر كان لا يزال يعمل علي،
collapsing my other lung,
انهيار رئتي الأخرى
and I managed to, by hitting that guy, to get a minute.
وتمكنت، بضرب هذا الرجل، من الحصول على دقيقة واحدة.
I ran down the street and collapsed,
جريت إلى أسفل الشارع وسقطت،
and the ambulance guys intubated me on the sidewalk
ورجال الإسعاف سحبوني من على الرصيف
and let the trauma room know
وأبلغوا غرفة الطوارئ
they had an incoming.
أنه سيأتيهم مصاب
And one of the
وإحدى
side effects of having major massive blood loss
الآثار الجانبية من فقدان كمية ضخمة من الدم
is you get tunnel vision,
هو ضعف الرؤية الجانبية
so I remember being on the stretcher
ولذا فأنا أتذكر أنني كنت على النقالة
and having a little nickel-sized cone of vision,
ولدي رؤية محدودة جداً بحجم مخروط قطره قطر عملة صغيرة،
and I was moving my head around
وكنت أحرك رأسي
and we got to St. Vincent's,
ووصلنا إلى "سانت فنسنت"،
and we're racing down this hallway,
ومسرعين إلى أسفل هذا الممر،
and I see the lights going,
وأنا أرى الأضواء تذهب،
and it's a peculiar effect of memories like that.
وأثر غريب من الذكريات مثل ذلك.
They don't really go to the usual place that memories go.
حقاً أنهم لا يذهبون إلى المكان المعتاد الذي تذهب إليه الذكريات.
They kind of have this vault where they're stored in high-def,
لديهم نوع من هذا المدفن حيث يتم تخزينها به عالية الوضوح،
and George Lucas did all the sound effects. (Laughter)
و"جورج لوكاس" فعل جميع المؤثرات الصوتية. (ضحك)
So sometimes, remembering them, it's like,
حتى في بعض الأحيان، تذكرها، أنها مثل،
it's not like any other kind of memories.
أنها ليست مثل أي نوع آخر من الذكريات.
And I get into the trauma room,
واصل إلى غرفة الصدمات،
and they're waiting for me, and the lights are there,
وهم ينتظرونني، والأضواء كانت هناك،
and I'd been able to breathe a little more now,
ولقد كنت حينها قادراً على التنفس أكثر قليلاً ،
because the blood has left, had been filling up my lungs
لأن الدم ذهب، الذي كان يملأ رئتي
and I was having a very hard time breathing,
وكنت أعاني من صعوبة شديدة في التنفس،
but now it's kind of gone into the stretcher.
ولكن الآن كأنها نوعاً ما ذهبت إلى النقالة،
And I said, "Is there anything I can do to help?"
وقلت، " هل هناك أي شيء يمكنني القيام به للمساعدة؟"
and — (Laughter) —
و--(ضحك)-
the nurse kind of had a hysterical laugh, and
والممرضة كأنها ضحكت ضحك هستيري
I'm turning my head trying to see everybody,
أنا أقلب رأسي في محاولة لرؤية الجميع،
and I had this weird memory of being in college
وكان لدي تلك الذكرى الغريبة في الكلية
and raising,
وجمع،
raising money for the flood victims of Bangladesh,
جمع الأموال لضحايا الفيضانات في بنغلاديش،
and then I look over and my anesthesiologist
ثم أنظر إلى دكتور التخدير
is clamping the mask on me, and I think,
يضع القناع علي ، وأنا أفكر،
"He looks Bangladeshi," — (Laughter) —
"يبدو أنه بنجلاديشي،"--(ضحك) —
and I just have those two facts, and I just think,
ولدي فقط تلك الحقيقتين، وأنا فقط أفكر،
"This could work somehow." (Laughter)
"هذا يمكن أن يعمل بطريقة ما." (ضحك)
And then I go out, and
وثم أخرج، و
they work on me for the rest of the night,
وهم يعلمون علي لبقية الليل،
and I needed about 40 units of blood to keep me there
وأنا أحتاج إلى حوالي 40 وحدة من الدم لأبقى على قيد الحياة
while they did their work,
في الوقت الذين كانو يعملون عملهم،
and the surgeon took out about a third of my intestines,
والجراح أخرج حوالي ثلث أمعائي،
my cecum, organs I didn't know that I had,
معيي الأعور، أعضاء لم أكن أعرف أنه كان عندي،
and he later told me one of the last things he did
وفي وقت لاحق قال لي أحد الأشياء الأخيرة التي فعلها
while he was in there was to remove my appendix for me,
عندما كان يجري الجراحة أزال لي الزائدة الدودية،
which I thought was great, you know,
وأعتقدت أنه كان شيئاً رائعاً، كما تعلمون،
just a little tidy thing there at the end. (Laughter)
فقط تنظيف بسيط هناك في النهاية. (ضحك)
And I came to in the morning.
وأستيقظت في الصباح.
Out of anesthetic, he had let them know
صحوت من التخدير، وقال لهم الجراح أن يبلغوه
that he wanted to be there, and he had given me
أنه أراد أن يكون هناك، وأنه أعطى لي
about a two percent chance of living.
حوالي الاثنين بالمائة فرصة في الحياة.
So he was there when I woke up,
لذا كان هناك عندما استيقظت،
and it was, waking up was like
وكان، الاستيقاظ كان مثل
breaking through the ice into a frozen lake of pain.
كسر من خلال الجليد في بحيرة مجمدة من الألم.
It was that enveloping,
كان يغلفني الألم
and there was only one spot that didn't hurt
وكان هناك منطقة واحدة فقط لاتؤلم
worse than anything I'd ever felt,
أسوأ من أي شيء شعرت به من قبل،
and it was my instep,
و قد كانت مشط رجلي،
and he was holding the arch of my foot
و كان يمسك قوس قدمي
and rubbing the instep with his thumb.
ويفرك رجلي مع إبهامه.
And I looked up, and he's like,
ونظرت إلى أعلى، وكأنه يقول
"Good to see you,"
"من الجيد أن أراك،"
and I was trying to remember what had happened
وكنت أحاول أن أتذكر ما حدث
and trying to get my head around everything,
وأحاول تذكر كل شيء،
and the pain was just overwhelming, and he said,
وكان الألم شديداً، وقال:
"You know, we didn't cut your hair. I thought
"هل تعلم، لم نقص شعرك. فكرت
you might have gotten strength from your hair like Samson,
أنك حصلت على قوة من شعرك مثل شمشون،
and you're going to need all the strength you can get."
وأنت ستكون في حاجة إلى كل القوة التي يمكن أن تحصل عليها ".
And in those days, my hair was down to my waist,
وفي تلك الأيام، كان شعري يصل إلى خصري،
I drove a motorcycle, I was unmarried,
كنت أسوق دراجة نارية، وكنت غير متزوج،
I owned a bar, so those were different times. (Laughter)
كنت أملك باراً ، تلك كانت أوقات مختلفة. (ضحك)
But
لكن
I had three days of life support,
كنت على أجهزة الانعاش لمدة ثلاث أيام
and everybody was expecting,
والجميع كان يتوقع
due to just the massive amount of what they had had to do
نظراً لحجم الأمر الذي اضطروا إلى القيام به
that I wasn't going to make it,
أنني لن أنجو
so it was three days of
لذا كان لمدة ثلاثة أيام
everybody was either waiting for me to die or poop,
وكان الجميع ينتظر إما أن أموت أوأتبرز،
and — (Laughter) —
و--(ضحك)-
when I finally pooped, then that somehow,
عندما أخيراً تبرزت، في ذلك الوقت بطريقة ما،
surgically speaking, that's like you crossed some good line,
من منطلق جراحي، هذا يعتبر مثل عبور خط جيد،
and, um — (Laughter) —
، وأم--(ضحك)-
on that day, the surgeon came in
في ذلك اليوم، جاء الطبيب الجراح
and whipped the sheet off of me.
وسحب غطاء الفراش فوقي بسرعة.
He had three or four friends with him,
كان معه ثلاثة أو أربعة أصدقاء
and he does that, and they all look,
وهو يفعل ذلك، وكلهم ينظرون،
and there was no infection,
ولم يكن هناك التهاب،
and they bend over me and they're poking and prodding,
و انحنوا علي وبدأوا يضغطون بأصابعهم
and they're like, "There's no hematomas, blah blah,
ويقولون، "ليس هناك أورام دموية، بلاه بلاه،
look at the color," and they're talking amongst themselves
انظروا إلى اللون "، و يتحدثون فيما بينهم
and I'm, like, this restored automobile
وأنا، مثل، السيارة المعدلة
that he's just going, "Yeah, I did that." (Laughter)
والجراح يقول، "نعم، لقد فعلت ذلك." (ضحك)
And it was just,
وكان
it was amazing, because these guys are high-fiving him
كان مدهشاً، لأن هؤلاء الشباب يضربون كفه
over how good I turned out, you know? (Laughter)
يحيونه على أنني أصبحت بصحة جيدة، تعلمون؟ (ضحك)
And it's my zipper, and I've still got the staples in
وهي أعضائي، ولازالت
and everything.
وكل شيء.
And
و
later on, when I got out
وفي وقت لاحق عندما خرجت
and the flashbacks and the
وذكريات الماضي و
nightmares were giving me a hard time,
الكوابيس أعطتني وقتاً عصيبا،
I went back to him
عدت إليه
and I was sort of asking him,
وكنت نوعا ما أسأله،
you know, what am I gonna do?
كما تعلمون، ماذا سأفعل؟
And I think, kind of, as a surgeon, he basically said,
وأعتقد أنه، نوعاً من، كطبيب جراح، قال
"Kid, I saved your life.
"يا فتى، أنقذت حياتك.
Like, now you can do whatever you want, like,
مثل، الآن يمكنك أن تفعل ما تشاء،
you gotta get on with that.
يجب أن تتعود على الوضع.
It's like I gave you a new car
كأنني أعطيتك سيارة جديدة
and you're complaining about not finding parking.
وأنت تشكو من عدم العثور على موقف للسيارة.
Like, just, go out, and, you know, do your best.
فقط، أخرج، وأنت تعلم، ابذل قصارى جهدك.
But you're alive. That's what it's about."
ولكن أنت على قيد الحياة. هذا هو أهم شيء ".
And then I hear, "Bing-bong," and the subway doors
وثم أسمع، "بنج بونج"، وأبواب مترو الإنفاق
are closing, and my stop is next, and I look at these kids,
وتغلق، ومحطتي ستكون المحطة القادمة، وأنظر إلى هؤلاء الشباب،
and I go, I think to myself,
وأذهب، أفكر في نفسي،
"I'm going to lift my shirt up
"سأرفع قميصي
and show them," — (Laughter) —
وأعرض لهم، "--(ضحك)-
and then I think, "No, this is the New York City subway,
ثم أفكر، "لا، هذا هو مترو الإنفاق في مدينة نيويورك،
that's going to lead to other things." (Laughter)
هذا سوف يؤدي إلى أشياء أخرى. " (ضحك)
And so I just think, they got their lecture to go to.
وفقط أفكر، لديهم محاضرة للذهاب إليها.
I step off, I'm standing on the platform,
وأخرج، وأنا واقف على منصة القطارات،
and I feel my index finger
وأنا أشعر بإصبعي السبابة
in
في
the first scar that I ever got,
الندبة الأولى التي حصلت عليها،
from my umbilical cord,
من حبلي السري،
and then around that, is traced
وحول ذلك، تتبع
the last scar that I got
ندبة الماضي التي حصلت على
from my surgeon,
من طبيبي الجراح،
and I think that, that chance encounter
وأعتقد أن ذلك، أن فرصة اللقاء
with those kids on the street with their knives
مع هؤلاء الأطفال في الشارع بتلك السكاكين
led me
أوصلتني
to my surgical team,
إلى فريقي الجراحي،
and their training
وتدريبهم
and their skill
ومهاراتهم
and, always, a little bit of luck
ودائما، قليلاً من الحظ
pushed back against chaos.
يصد الفوضى
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Very lucky to be here. Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. محظوظ جداً أن أكون هنا. شكرا. (تصفيق)